hey guys it's Justin and today we're
going to be talking about what makes a
successful student so I've been helping
students become more academically
capable and confident and increase their
studying efficiency for quite a while
now and there's definitely some trends
that I've noticed between my students
that are more successful and the ones
that aren't now when I say success I'm
really talking about just academic
performance and academic achievement
here we're not going to go into the
whole Myriad of different definitions of
what success really means I know that
that's a whole other topic but we're
already talking about just being able to
have a high level of academic
achievement not only in high school or
early University but later on in
education as well with more advanced or
competitive degrees what is it that sets
a successful student apart from a not so
successful student before I share with
you my insights let's actually take a
look at the research and what that says
first
and when we do a search for student
achievement or academic achievement we
find that there are a lot of articles
that talk about managerial things for
example how good are the teachers how
good are these schools and all of that
sort of things things outside of really
the students control so what we really
want to be thinking about is what are
the things that a student can directly
control an influence that will change
their ability to be successful now when
we look at the research that's on this
topic there are certain terms that start
popping out to us and these are the
terms that we need to become familiar
with we see words like deeper learning
coming up very often in the research now
this isn't to be confused with deep
learning when it comes to machine
learning and artificial intelligence
which is a completely separate Topic in
fact deep learning when we're talking
about students and student learning is
actually talking about the ability to
make more meaningful connections and
another common terminology that's used
alongside deep learning that we can find
is something called Active Learning and
another term called threshold Concepts
and this is really where the money is
going to be so threshold Concepts refer
to Core Concepts in a subject where
understanding these Concepts is key to
transforming the way students understand
a whole subject a threshold concept can
be described as transformative probably
irreversible integrative and sometimes
bounded to particular disciplines and
potentially Troublesome so these would
be things that cause you to have a light
bulb moment once you've already crossed
over it now threshold concepts are an
incredibly important part of learning
and it's one of the first principles
that I learned that really attracted my
attention because it cleanly explains so
many different complicated aspects of
learning and actually it's where I
started researching from and then built
outwards to develop the knowledge that I
have now so really threshold Concepts is
talking about a concept that provides
some kind of barrier to understanding
something a certain way it's important
not to get confused with this and just a
difficult concept a difficult concept is
just something that you find it hard to
wrap your head around it may just be
difficult to understand a threshold
concept is actually a concept that
allows you to access an entire way of
looking at it you're not necessarily
learning anything new you're learning
the same information but you're suddenly
able to see it in a way that you
previously weren't able to see it and so
the experience of encountering a
threshold concept is like stumbling over
a threshold Block in the dark and you're
suddenly lost and confused and you don't
know where you are and you're
disorientated you're listening to the
teacher and suddenly you have no idea
what they're talking about anymore and
you're lost or you're reading a book and
suddenly you have no idea what the page
you just read is about you're suddenly
lost and you don't know really why but
somewhere along the way
you lost your way
English do you speak it but
somewhere along the way you
somewhere along the way you got lost
and so when you overcome a threshold
concept we often talk about this as a
light bulb moment and so when we're able
to elicit these light bulb moments more
readily more under our control and more
frequently we're able to increase the
speed of our learning so we want to be
able to access and overcome these
threshold Concepts as quickly as
possible to become a learner who just
gets things a lot faster and in order to
do that we fundamentally need to
understand that there are a few aspects
of learning that are fixed for example
learning tends to be what's called
recursive what that means is that you're
not learning it the perfect way the
first time you're often learning
something once and then going back onto
it to learn it again and again it's not
to say that you didn't learn it properly
the first time it's just that certain
things make more sense when you've
learned more already or the pieces have
kind of come into place a little bit
more you're able to see the big picture
and so those details that previously
didn't make sense to to you now they
suddenly make a lot more sense so
learning is recursive in nature and
that's the first important point we need
to understand and the second part is the
direct opposite which is that it's an
excursive approach which means that
there is a Learning Journey that occurs
that has allowances for diversions what
that means is that you can progress
through the material and you don't have
to always go in the same straight linear
line you can go back and forth you can
have multiple different ways that you're
actually learning something and so what
that means is that you don't have to
learn everything the best way the first
time it doesn't have to be a straight
line from beginning to end not only are
you going and then recursing back but
you're also going and then being pulled
on a side tangent and taking diversions
and side routes so the learning process
is very non-linear it's inherently very
in a way messy and disorganized and
chaotic but actually it's not truly
chaotic it's only chaotic when you rest
restrict it to the order that a book or
a lecture might lay it out for you
because it's so clean in a book or a
lecture or a video but in reality it is
ordered in that it's in the order that
our brain is able to make sense of it so
what that means is that initially the
book might lay out a concept as a then B
then C then D but maybe in reality it
makes more sense for you to learn it as
B then a then D then back to a and then
C and that will be the order that your
brain finds makes the most sense so we
need to allow for that to occur in
learning and so this thing called Active
Learning which has been well studied is
a way for us to tap into these threshold
Concepts and it includes but it's not
limited to class pose quizzes group
discussions game based learning and
really it's anything that allows us to
do that kind of chaotic messy learning
in a way that keeps us engaged in our
head and thinking and active rather than
passive which would be just sitting
there sort of letting the information
absorb and rip through almost through
sort of like an osmosis which it doesn't
really happen that way so what are the
techniques that allow us to engage in
this Active Learning in a sustainable
consistent way that anyone can start
applying straight away to take their
first second to 100th step to becoming a
more effective learner well let's break
down those steps as you might expect
there's actually a number of different
techniques that we can use and they're
all kind of effective but they all have
a certain Trend behind them so what I'm
going to teach you is not the technique
itself but the trend and a few examples
of techniques that follow these trends
so pretty much every single good learner
is going to be able to do the following
five things so these are the five
attributes of a good learner the first
thing that a good learner is able to do
is they're able to include something
called priming which is often just
called pre-study but they're not quite
the same thing now there's actually lots
of different forms of what's called
priming and so when I use the term I'm
using it pretty Loosely what I'm talking
about with priming is specifically the
ability to look at a certain piece of
information and instead of learning it
in full rigor from the beginning all the
way to the bottom what we do is we
quickly scan the text first and get a
general understanding and a framework
for how to think about this before we
even know what to know so this could be
as simple as going through and reading
the headings looking at some of the
diagrams some of the images that seem
relevant and important and making a very
simple wireframe mind map on how the big
pictures connect together now the most
important thing here is that you don't
want to get sucked into all of the
detail if you do you're gonna sacrifice
that big picture understanding which is
the primary purpose of this step and
what this means is that because you have
a better big picture understanding
you're going to be able to make those
light bulb moments more easily because
information that started at the
beginning you're going to have a general
idea of how that might be relevant to
the things you learn later on and at the
end so priming is something that can
increase your learning efficiency by a
huge amount and this is where a lot of
people have a limitation with their
learning and this is another area where
if you were to make an improvement you'd
probably make a disproportionate
increase in your studying efficiency
compared to some of the other areas that
you can improve on so this is definitely
step number one for most students
the second aspect is when we're actually
in the class or the lecture itself and
how we stay attentive and active during
the learning event which I'll just call
event here so if you ever felt sleepy or
drowsy or you're not paying attention or
losing focus or by the time the class or
lecture finishes you still don't really
know what the hell is going on then this
is probably the area that you should be
paying attention to and there are a few
different ways that we can do this one
of the easiest ways that we engage that
level of activity is first of all
understanding that it takes effort to be
engaged like if someone throws a ball at
you you can't catch it just by
being alive and existing you have to
actually hold up your hands and prepare
to catch the ball and this is sort of
how we need to think about information
when someone is speaking to us or when
we're reading we need to be able to
catch the information that we're
consuming if we don't catch it it's just
gonna hit us and we will think we have
sort of absorbed it but we didn't it's
more like we just got assaulted with
information and the way that we can do
this is through a number of different
ways an easy way that if you're sitting
there listening to someone speaking and
increasing your engagement is by asking
them questions either out loud or even
just inside your own head and you want
to be asking questions a lot lots and
lots of questions multiple questions
every minute so whatever information
comes in to your brain to be processed
in whatever way take that information
and think what are the questions that I
want to ask about this and there are
certain editions at a higher yield than
other questions so for example let's say
that we learned something about a cell
or about a muscle tissue we could ask
the question of what is this muscle
tissue where does it come from what are
the features of this tissue or this cell
and yes those are questions but they're
not as good as questions that ask about
why or how and this is because why and
how questions Force us to relate it back
to
the big picture and the big picture
again is what's going to allow us to
make those light bulb moments faster so
hopefully you're seeing a trend with
these techniques so when we ask a why or
how question it actually causes us to
relate that information at a higher
Mastery of knowledge and we are not only
needing to understand a single concept
but the relationship that that has with
multiple other related Concepts to see
how does it fit together so asking why
questions or how come these questions
are going to be a lot more high yield
than questions that are more like what
or very superficial looking the third
aspect if you're following along the
chronology is going to be after the
event so this is when is the next time
you revise that information now good
students are going to have their first
revision within 12 hours of the initial
learning event and there's research
showing that the longer you wait the
more you're going to forget and that
first window of first having consumed
that knowledge and then consolidating it
straight away is more important than the
time that comes after it so if you
revise it on the first day that's going
to produce more of an impact than if you
were to revise it on
doesn't make sense so if you were to
revise it on that first day you're
getting disproportionately higher
benefit than leaving it for two days
which is only an additional day
difference but that first day is just
more important so ideally you want to be
consolidating that information before
you even go to sleep that night because
then you get to maximize on something
called Sleep dependent memory
consolidation which is basically in a
way
studying while you're asleep kind of but
not really and the fourth thing is
actually related directly to this which
is the way that you do this revision so
the technique that you use when you
revise is really important we want to
make sure that it's as active as
possible and that it relates it back to
the big picture again so the techniques
that we want to use here are going to be
ones that accentuate the relationship of
all of these details with the big
picture so it means taking information
that we've learned from the lecture or
from the class and that we've picked up
from our pre-reading and our priming
which I just represent as this sort of
lattice network of knowledge and we want
to find a way to represent this in a
connected big picture way and so a great
way of doing that is using a mind map
now if you're not familiar with how to
do a mind map I've got a video
explaining how to make the perfect mind
map which definitely check out as well
but there are a few guidelines to how
you should do your notes and how you
should do this revision that generally
you should study whether you use a mind
map or not the first thing is that you
should try to make your notes reasonably
non-verbal that means not using too many
words and the reason is because our
brain is divided into multiple
hemispheres and you get a larger degree
of learning when the knowledge is not
just sitting in one area of the brain
but we're able to process it in multiple
different areas of the brain using not
words to express an idea allows us to
use parts of our brain that would
normally not be activated so you want to
make words and sentences a last resort
when it comes to writing notes and
related to that we actually want to make
these notes reasonably minimal so
there's a myth that in order to learn
effectively you need to write lots of
notes but this isn't actually the case
humans have been learning for a really
long time before we even learn how to
read and write especially to the level
that we do now learning is a process
that occurs really authentically and our
brain is really good at it so we don't
actually need to be right writing things
down to learn in fact it can actually
make it worse when you write too many
notes you reduce this thing called
cognitive load and that's sort of the
level of confusion in our brain while we
are trying to learn something and
confusion is actually a good thing when
it comes to learning we want to optimize
the level of confusion not too much
because then we're too lost but not too
little because then our brain isn't
trying to figure it out and organize the
information and it's this process of
organizing and relating it to the big
picture that allows us to learn more
effectively so we want to make that
cognitive load or confusion in that
perfect optimal band and in order to do
this we can do something called delayed
note-taking which is when instead of
writing everything down straight away we
simply just hold it off for a bit and
keep it in our head think about it let
that confusion settle in and let our
brain do its thing asking lots of
questions asking those how and why
questions and then figuring out how it
all fits in to simplify by the
information and then that new simplified
information we can then write down so a
technique that a lot of students will
use is something like a summary sheet
but they often do this after already
having written a bunch of copious notes
well people will paraphrase their notes
in a certain way but we can really skip
all of those early stages and we can
jump straight to the point where we're
writing our simplified notes and we can
do all of that simplification not on
paper because it takes a lot of time we
can do that in our head and not only is
it saving time it's also training our
brain to be able to do that Learning
Without relying on writing down
everything and when we get rid of that
sort of uncertainty and fear of having
to write constantly in order to learn we
unlock an enormous huge opportunity for
more effective learning moving forward
and a lot of the more Advanced
Techniques rely on your ability to not
need to be writing down constantly and
the fifth and final aspect is in the
revision Vision leading up to a test or
an exam and this simply means that you
need a revised material in a way that's
actually effective so this pre-test or
pre-exam revision
is the final part and there are a few
guidelines that we can follow here as
well the first is that we want to make
sure that it's always challenging we
have a tendency when we're learning to
only really test ourselves and challenge
the things that we already know but the
weakness obviously there is that we're
systematically going to miss the things
that we're weakest on which is sort of
counter-intuitive always make the
revision challenging in a meaningful way
and easy ways to make this challenging
that good Learners will use is by using
things that use recall and recall is
simply when you're taking something from
memory and recalling it rather than just
recognizing it so for example if I hold
up a pin you can look at it and you
recognize it it's a pen but it doesn't
mean that you'll be able to draw a
perfect replica of this pin so our
ability to recognize is usually much
greater than our ability to recall and
we don't want to be studying in a way
that's unnecessarily easy because
there's no real learning going on there
and when we're in a test or an exam
we're getting tested on our ability to
recall so at a minimum we should always
be trying to recall and in my view there
is no place for recognition based
revision anywhere and anyone's revision
strategy we also want to learn in a way
that is different each time and the
reason we want to learn in a different
way is because we want to be testing
those connections and that knowledge in
a new and unique way if we learn
something the same way every single time
then we actually saturate out the amount
of learning that we can get from that
particular mode so re-reading notes is
one of the worst ways that you can study
because not only is it not challenging
it's also the same method of learning
that we used the first time which was
just reading and it's also using Oni
recognition rather than recall so while
rewriting notes based on memory would be
better than just re-reading because
because it uses recall it would be even
better to try to represent our notes
through Doodles or diagrams or mind maps
or some other form a great technique
that most of my students will use is
teaching and you teach as if there's
someone legitimately sitting next to you
an imaginary student who doesn't know
anything and by teaching it forces you
not only to recall it forces you not
only to draw and annotate while you
teach in a way that's different to how
your notes look but it also forces you
to look at the big picture and figure
out what's the most effective way to
teach this person this topic which means
that you're again relating it to the big
picture and finding those weaknesses so
every good learner is going to be able
to have a reasonable level of Competency
or Mastery in these five aspects the
priming the event itself and maintaining
your engagements throughout it when you
do your first revision how you do your
first revision and the subsequent
revisions that come after it this is the
foundation and on top of that we add
other things like space repetition or
more specific techniques like flash
cards or how to write specific mind maps
or active listening or active reading
strategies or how to do the priming and
pre-study more effectively but all of
those are fundamentally sitting on a
scaffold of these foundations and if
you're able to do all of these in this
way you're going to see massive
improvements in your efficiency of study
but as we all know learning is always
individual and what might work for some
people doesn't necessarily work the same
way for others the things that I've
talked about today are really considered
the fundamentals and I haven't really
met a student in the thousands of
students that I've worked with where
these principles fundamentally didn't
work for so I'd love to know what your
experience has been have you tried some
of these have you nod and are you
excited to have you learned something
new from this video whatever your
experiences leave a comment down below
and let me know I'd love to hear your
thoughts on this if you liked this type
of video make sure to hit that Thumbs Up
Hit hit the Subscribe button and I'll
see you in that next video
[Music]